<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<activity id="57" moduleid="4875" modulename="book" contextid="14182">
  <book id="57">
    <name>Principle 4: Various sources of energy can be used to power human activities, and often this energy must be transferred from source to destination</name>
    <intro>&lt;p&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;</intro>
    <introformat>1</introformat>
    <numbering>0</numbering>
    <customtitles>1</customtitles>
    <timecreated>1433776985</timecreated>
    <timemodified>1433776985</timemodified>
    <chapters>
      <chapter id="461">
        <pagenum>1</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 4: Various sources of energy can be used to power human activities, and often this energy must be transferred from source to destination</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Principle 4: Various sources of energy can be used to power human activities, and often this energy must be transferred from source to destination.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/icon_p4.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="Icon of a power line to represent Principle 4 of the Energy Literacy Framework" style="margin-left: 20px; margin-right: 20px; float: right;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources of energy, including non-renewable energy sources, such as petroleum, natural gas, coal, and nuclear energy, and renewable energy sources such as sunlight, wind, water, and geothermal energy, are harnessed and transformed to power human activities. This principle’s concepts explore issues related to generating energy, transporting energy, and storing energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Principle 4’s Fundamental Concepts on the next page to build your understanding of the concepts and information included in each principle. You can use the Fundamental &lt;br /&gt;Concepts to inform your instruction related to this principle.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1433781569</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="462">
        <pagenum>2</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 4’s Fundamental Concepts</title>
        <content>&lt;h1&gt;Principle 4’s Fundamental Concepts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fundamental Concepts of Principle 4 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.1  Humans transfer and transform energy from the environment into forms useful for human endeavors&lt;/strong&gt;. The primary sources of energy in the environment include fuels like coal, oil, natural gas, uranium, and biomass. All primary source fuels except biomass are non-renewable. Primary sources also include renewable sources such as sunlight, wind, moving water, and geothermal energy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.2  Human use of energy is subject to limits and constraints&lt;/strong&gt;. Industry, transportation, urban development, agriculture, and most other human activities are closely tied to the amount and kind of energy available. The availability of energy resources is constrained by the distribution of natural resources, availability of affordable technologies, socioeconomic policies, and socioeconomic status.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.3  Fossil fuels and biofuels are organic matter that contain energy captured from sunlight&lt;/strong&gt;. The energy in fossil fuels such as oil, natural gas, and coal comes from energy that producers like plants, algae, and cyanobacteria captured from sunlight long ago. The energy in biofuels such as food, wood, and ethanol comes from energy that producers captured from sunlight very recently. Energy stored in these fuels is released during chemical reactions, such as combustion and respiration, which also release carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.4  Humans transport energy from place to place&lt;/strong&gt;. Fuels are often not used at their source but are transported, sometimes over long distances. Fuels are transported primarily by pipelines, trucks, ships, and trains. Electrical energy can be generated from a variety of energy resources and can be transformed into almost any other form of energy. Electric circuits are used to distribute energy to distant locations. Electricity is not a primary source of energy, but an energy carrier.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.5  Humans generate electricity in multiple ways&lt;/strong&gt;. When a magnet moves or a magnetic field changes relative to a coil of wire, electrons are induced to flow in the wire. Most human generation of electricity happens in this way. Electrons can also be induced to flow through direct interaction with light particles; this is the basis upon which a solar cell operates. Other means of generating electricity include electrochemical, piezoelectric, and thermoelectric.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.6  Humans intentionally store energy for later use in a number of different ways&lt;/strong&gt;. Examples include batteries, water reservoirs, compressed air, hydrogen, and thermal storage. Storage of energy involves many technological, environmental, and social challenges.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.7  Different sources of energy and the different ways energy can be transformed, transported, and stored each have different benefits and drawbacks&lt;/strong&gt;. A given energy system, from source to sink, will have an inherent level of energy efficiency, monetary cost, and environmental risk. Each system will also have national security, access, and equity implications. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434466250</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="463">
        <pagenum>3</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Strategies for Connecting Principle 4 with Learners’ Lives</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Strategies for Connecting Principle 4 with Learners’ Lives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle provides many opportunities to connect the content with learners’ lives. From seeing power lines to turning on a gas stove, we interact with energy from different sources every day. Look for opportunities throughout your lessons to build on learners’ prior knowledge and experiences with the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching strategies include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have learners map out the paths of different types of energy from source to end use. In beginning or intermediate level classrooms, place signs in your classroom that have the name of physical locations or checkpoints in the movement of energy products (e.g., oil source, oil refinery, pipeline, oil tankers, pipeline, rail). Learners select the order in which energy moves through the different checkpoints. In more advanced classrooms, have small groups map the paths using a white board. Groups analyze any differences or similarities in the pathway they have drawn. Select at least one fossil fuel, such as oil, and one renewable energy source. To provide learners with an example, show this &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/eere/wind/how-distributed-wind-works" target="_blank"&gt;graphic model&lt;/a&gt; of how distributed wind works.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use SERC’s “&lt;a href="http://serc.carleton.edu/NAGTWorkshops/energy/activities/32718.html" target="_blank"&gt;From Grid to Home” lesson&lt;/a&gt; to analyze energy use and costs related to bringing energy into learner’s homes. The materials can be modified for your classroom level, as needed. This lesson scaffolds learners as they engage with scientific data presented in different formats, including pie charts, tables, and bar graphs. This helps support &lt;strong&gt;CCR ELA Reading Anchor Standard 7:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Integrate and evaluate content presented in diverse media and formats, including visually and quantitatively, as well as in words.&lt;/em&gt; (Pimentel, 2013, p.19)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have each learner bring in a lightbulb from home. Learners begin by identifying the type of lightbulb, watts, and other characteristics based on observation. Next, learners research their lightbulbs and create a pro/con list about the lightbulb's benefits and weaknesses. To connect with a math lesson, learners can calculate the power of the different types of lightbulbs or how much it costs to use that lightbulb in a year. You can direct learners to the &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/energysaver/articles/lighting-choices-save-you-money" target="_blank"&gt;Energy 101:Lighting Choices&lt;/a&gt; video to understand the basic differences between lightbulbs. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="450" height="341" alt="Photo of a refuse truck fueling up at a Clean Energy station. " src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/WasteTruck.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;Natural gas is an economical, clean-burning, and environmentally friendly alternative to diesel. (Photo by Clean Energy. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;.) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435855845</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="464">
        <pagenum>4</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Online Resources for Teaching Principle 4</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Online Resources for Teaching Principle 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet has a wealth of resources on renewable and non-renewable energy that teachers can incorporate into their instruction. Teaching materials on this principle include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7CU9iqm2Hcw" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Literacy Essential Principle #4&lt;/a&gt; video, from the U.S. Department of Energy and American Geoscience Institute, provides an overview of the principle, its concepts, and examples.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.energy101.com/free-educational-tools/videos/" target="_blank"&gt;Energy 101's video series &lt;/a&gt;is comprised of short introductory YouTube videos on fossil fuels and renewable energy sources, as well as how electricity is created and delivered. Videos are a great way to get your class started or wrap up a class. (See these topics: II: Fossil Fuels, III: Renewable Energy, and V: Electricity.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informational booklets, activity sheets, games, and other tools for teaching about renewable energy sources, transmission of energy, and electricity developed by the &lt;a href="http://www.cleanlineenergy.com/learn/teachers" target="_blank"&gt;NEED project&lt;/a&gt; are available at multiple levels.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency &lt;a href="http://oaspub.epa.gov/powpro/ept_pack.charts"&gt;Power Profiler&lt;/a&gt; allows learners to explore what energy source powers their electricity. This online interactive tool allows you to enter a zip code, identify your utility provider and instantly get interactive reports and graphs on your electricity source(s). Adult learners can explore their zip code, neighboring counties, and state data.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://cleanet.org/clean/literacy/energyquiz.html"&gt;Energy Awareness Quiz&lt;/a&gt; is an online interactive quiz from CLEAN that could be used to introduce new vocabulary or test learners’ knowledge.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.energy.gov/eere/education/downloads/energy-literacy-social-studies-guide-essential-principle-4"&gt;Energy Literacy Social Studies Guide for Principle 4&lt;/a&gt; helps learners create maps and make connections between energy sources and the electricity they use in their homes and communities. This activity helps learners understand how energy is converted into electricity and how that electricity powers our lives. It may be helpful to show an introductory video on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qEvq05gVRP0"&gt;how a coal plant works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435857073</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="465">
        <pagenum>5</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Summary of Principle 4&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 4 helps learners understand the differences between sources of energy and benefits and drawbacks of use for each of those sources. This principle offers an ideal opportunity to begin incorporating the human element into the energy discussion. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/Windmills.jpg" width="450" height="341" alt="Several wind turbines on Tehachapi Pass Wind Farm in California." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small; line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Tehachapi Pass Wind Farm in California. The 705-megawatt farm is composed of about 5,000 wind turbines. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small; line-height: 1.231;"&gt;(Photo by David Hicks / NREL. Source: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/" style="font-size: x-small; line-height: 1.231;"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small; line-height: 1.231;"&gt;) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #993300; line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Continue on to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="color: #993300; line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Principle 5: Energy decisions are influenced by economic, political, environmental, and social factors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434029001</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
    </chapters>
  </book>
</activity>