<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<activity id="60" moduleid="4878" modulename="book" contextid="14185">
  <book id="60">
    <name>Principle 7: The quality of life of individuals and societies is affected by energy choices</name>
    <intro>&lt;p&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;</intro>
    <introformat>1</introformat>
    <numbering>0</numbering>
    <customtitles>1</customtitles>
    <timecreated>1433794038</timecreated>
    <timemodified>1433794038</timemodified>
    <chapters>
      <chapter id="476">
        <pagenum>1</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 7: The quality of life of individuals and societies is affected by energy choices</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Principle 7: The quality of life of individuals and societies is affected by energy choices.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/icon_p7.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="Icon of a human being to represent Principle 7 of the Energy Literacy Framework." style="float: right; margin-left: 20px; margin-right: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle makes direct connections between energy use and quality of life. Factors affecting individuals and society's quality of life includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;economic security&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;national security&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;environmental quality&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dependence on fossil fuels&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access to energy resources&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vulnerability to impacts of energy choices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The type of energy, for example solar power or hydro-electric power versus electricity, has important implications on economic opportunity. The environmental impacts of energy decisions also have a disproportionate impact on vulnerable populations, such as the poor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Principle 7’s Fundamental Concepts on the next page to build your understanding of the concepts and information included in each principle. You can use the Fundamental Concepts to inform your instruction related to this principle.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434471228</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="477">
        <pagenum>2</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 7’s Fundamental Concepts</title>
        <content>&lt;h1&gt;Principle 7’s Fundamental Concepts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fundamental Concepts of Principle 7 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.1  Economic security is impacted by energy choices&lt;/strong&gt;. Individuals and society continually make energy choices that have economic consequences. These consequences come in the form of monetary cost in general and in the form of price fluctuation and instability specifically.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.2  National security is impacted by energy choices&lt;/strong&gt;. The security of a nation is dependent, in part, on the sources of that nation’s energy supplies. For example, a nation that has diverse sources of energy that come mostly from within its borders is more secure than a nation largely dependent on foreign energy supplies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.3  Environmental quality is impacted by energy choices&lt;/strong&gt;. Energy choices made by humans have environmental consequences. The quality of life of humans and other organisms on Earth can be significantly affected by those consequences.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.4  Increasing demand for and limited supplies of fossil fuels affect quality of life&lt;/strong&gt;. Fossil fuels provide the vast majority of the world’s energy. &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;Fossil fuel&lt;/span&gt; supplies are limited. If society has not transitioned to sources of energy that are renewable before depleting Earth’s fossil fuel supplies, it will find itself in a situation where energy demand far exceeds energy supply. This situation will have many social and economic consequences.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.5  Access to energy resources affects quality of life&lt;/strong&gt;. Access to energy resources, or lack thereof, affects human health, access to education, socioeconomic status, gender equality, global partnerships, and the environment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.6  Some populations are more vulnerable to impacts of energy choices than others&lt;/strong&gt;. Energy decisions have economic, social, and environmental consequences. Poor, marginalized, or underdeveloped populations can most benefit from positive consequences and are the most susceptible to negative consequences.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434544534</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="478">
        <pagenum>3</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Strategies for Integrating Energy Topics with Other Subjects</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Strategies for Integrating Energy Topics with Other Subjects&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are opportunities for interdisciplinary instruction throughout an energy unit, Principle 7 includes interdisciplinary topics that relate to health, geography, history, sociology, and economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few ideas for teaching energy in an interdisciplinary manner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principle 7 illustrates the importance of energy choices and policies in hidden and obvious ways in our learners’ lives and in the lives of others. For example, the BBC’s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Tjy6x2wOqk" target="_blank"&gt;coverage of the 2008 Olympics&lt;/a&gt;, held in Beijing, China, highlighted the effects of the air quality on the Olympic athletes’ health and performance. Have learners view the video, then have them define air quality in groups by reviewing the &lt;a href="http://www.airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=aqibasics.aqi"&gt;Air Quality Index (AQI) reading&lt;/a&gt;. Next, have one group look at the &lt;a href="http://aqicn.org/city/beijing/"&gt;Real-Time Data AQI&lt;/a&gt; for Beijing and the nearest &lt;a href="http://www.airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=airnow.main" target="_blank"&gt;U.S. city&lt;/a&gt;. Have groups compare multiple U.S. cities and take notes based on the AQI color indicators. Ask groups to infer health risks for people when air quality is red or orange based on the AQI descriptions. Learners can begin to make the connection between air quality and health.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This principle provides many opportunities to talk about current events that are related to energy decisions, including the United States' relationship with oil-producing nations such as Russia and countries in the Middle East. Teachers can lead a discussion analyzing energy-related &lt;a href="http://www.usnews.com/cartoons/energy-policy-cartoons" target="_blank"&gt;political cartoons&lt;/a&gt;. This is an especially useful strategy if learners intend to take a high school equivalency exam, such as the GED&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;®&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Social Studies exam, which often features questions on political cartoons.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adult learners who have emigrated from other countries may be able to share their experiences with how quality of life is impacted by energy choices in their country of origin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434471335</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="479">
        <pagenum>4</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Capstone Activity for an Energy Unit</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Capstone Activity for an Energy Unit&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a capstone to your Energy unit, consider having learners write a five-paragraph essay defending an idea related to energy, drawing on and citing evidence learned throughout the unit. This is especially useful if learners have been providing written responses to discussion questions that allow them to practice comparing and contrasting, citing evidence, and developing arguments throughout the unit. This activity supports &lt;strong&gt;CCR ELA Writing Anchor 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Write arguments to support claims in an analysis of substantive topics or texts, using valid reasoning and relevant and sufficient evidence&lt;/em&gt;. (Pimentel, 2013, p. 22) If you plan to use writing prompts throughout your unit, share your ideas in the &lt;a href="https://community.lincs.ed.gov/discussion/online-course-using-writing-prompts-teach-energy-literacy" target="_blank"&gt;Reading and Writing group&lt;/a&gt; in the LINCS Community.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434471733</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="480">
        <pagenum>5</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Online Resources for Teaching Principle 7</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Online Resources for Teaching Principle 7&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet has a wealth of resources to help teachers integrate Principle 7 into their instruction, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OMTEANrtAQc" target="_blank"&gt; Energy Literacy Essential Principle #7&lt;/a&gt; video, from the U.S. Department of Energy and American Geoscience Institute, provides an overview of the principle, its concepts, and examples. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.worldof7billion.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/the-people-connection.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;The People Connection&lt;/a&gt; student reading, from Population Education, helps learners to understand the connection between human energy consumption, population growth and environmental impacts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help learners formulate and discuss their opinions related to energy sources, &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;consumption&lt;/span&gt;, and consequences for local and national policy using the &lt;a href="https://www.worldof7billion.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/7-Billion-Where-do-you-Stand.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;7 Billion: Where Do You Stand?&lt;/a&gt; lesson from Population Explosion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transportation is an easy topic to help learners make the connection between quality of life and energy. Transportation impacts our air, environment, water and economy. The Department of Energy’s Principle 7 &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2015/03/f20/EL7_SocStudiesGuides_AGI.pdf"&gt;Social Studies Guide&lt;/a&gt; helps learners explore these impacts. The Guide describes suggested lesson activities in detail.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLEAN provides &lt;a href="http://cleanet.org/clean/literacy/energy7.html" target="_blank"&gt;teaching suggestions and activities&lt;/a&gt; by grade level for each principle. Explore the materials and use or adapt them for your learners. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435857727</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="481">
        <pagenum>6</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Summary of Principle 7</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Summary of Principle 7&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 7 makes direct connections between energy use and quality of life, with both positive and negative impacts on societies. This principle offers a unique opportunity for teachers to help expand learners’ understanding and thinking beyond their own experiences with energy, so they begin to consider implications to the economy, security, and health of society as a whole.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/Bicycle.jpg" width="450" height="302" alt="Photo of a man on a recumbent bicycle." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;Hundreds of NREL employees opted for two wheels instead of four on Bike 2 Work Day. (Photo by Dennis Schroeder / NREL. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #993300;"&gt;Continue on to Course Conclusion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434029751</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
    </chapters>
  </book>
</activity>