<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<activity id="58" moduleid="4876" modulename="book" contextid="14183">
  <book id="58">
    <name>Principle 5: Energy decisions are influenced by economic, political, environmental, and social factors</name>
    <intro>&lt;p&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;</intro>
    <introformat>1</introformat>
    <numbering>0</numbering>
    <customtitles>1</customtitles>
    <timecreated>1433782422</timecreated>
    <timemodified>1433782422</timemodified>
    <chapters>
      <chapter id="466">
        <pagenum>1</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 5: Energy decisions are influenced by economic, political, environmental, and social factors</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Principle 5: Energy decisions are influenced by economic, political, environmental, and social factors.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/icon_p5.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="Icon of a scale to represent Principle 5 of the Energy Literacy Framework." style="margin-left: 20px; margin-right: 20px; float: right;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle covers topics about how and why energy decisions are made. Principle 5’s Fundamental Concepts on the next page focus on understanding the decision-making factors such as infrastructure, economic factors, policy factors, environmental factors, and social factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use these concepts to build your own understanding of the concepts and information included in each principle. You can then use them to inform your instruction related to this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The different branches of the federal government, including the U.S. Department of Energy and the Environmental Protection Agency, interact with state and local governments in making energy policies. There are several different types of policies that relate to energy, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;financial policies such as taxes, tax deductions, or subsidies&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;standards that companies must adhere to, such as efficiency standards or fuel economy standards for automobiles&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cap and trade for emissions, mandates&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;funding research and development to support invention and innovation in the field &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434467660</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="467">
        <pagenum>2</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 5’s Fundamental Concepts</title>
        <content>&lt;h1&gt;Principle 5’s Fundamental Concepts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fundamental Concepts of Principle 5 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.1  Decisions concerning the use of energy resources are made at many levels&lt;/strong&gt;. Humans make individual, community, national, and international energy decisions. Each of these levels of decision-making has some common and some unique aspects. Decisions made beyond the individual level often involve a formally established process of decision-making.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.2  Energy infrastructure has inertia&lt;/strong&gt;. The decisions that governments, corporations, and individuals made in the past have created today’s energy infrastructure. The large amount of money, time, and technology invested in these systems makes changing the infrastructure difficult, but not impossible. The decisions of one generation both provide and limit the range of possibilities open to future generations.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.3  Energy decisions can be made using a systems-based approach&lt;/strong&gt;. As individuals and societies make energy decisions, they can consider the costs and benefits of each decision. Some costs and benefits are more obvious than others. Identifying all costs and benefits requires a careful and informed systems-based approach to decision-making.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.4  Energy decisions are influenced by economic factors&lt;/strong&gt;. Monetary costs of energy affect energy decision making at all levels. Energy exhibits characteristics of both a commodity and a differentiable product. Energy costs are often subject to market fluctuations, and energy choices made by individuals and societies affect these fluctuations. Cost differences also arise as a result of differences between energy sources and as a result of tax-based incentives and rebates.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.5  Energy decisions are influenced by political factors&lt;/strong&gt;. Political factors play a role in energy decision making at all levels. These factors include, but are not limited to, governmental structure and power balances, actions taken by politicians, and partisan-based or self-serving actions taken by individuals and groups.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.6  Energy decisions are influenced by environmental factors&lt;/strong&gt;. Environmental costs of energy decisions affect energy decision-making at all levels. All energy decisions have environmental consequences. These consequences can be positive or negative.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.7  Energy decisions are influenced by social factors&lt;/strong&gt;. Questions of ethics, morals, and social norms affect energy decision-making at all levels. Social factors often involve economic, political, and environmental factors.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434467769</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="468">
        <pagenum>3</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Strategies for Incorporating Principle 5 into Classroom Instruction</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Strategies for Incorporating Principle 5 into Classroom Instruction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle is about decision-making regarding energy use. This principle offers opportunities to discuss solutions to energy challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few strategies for incorporating this principle into classroom instruction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begin the lesson by polling learners on their own decisions as energy users. For example, do they leave lights on when not at home? Why or why not? Answers may reflect economic or environmental reasons, which are factors that individuals, as well as governments, consider when making decisions around energy use.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because cost is a driver of many decisions around energy use, consider conducting interdisciplinary lessons with math or economics in which learners calculate costs of energy use.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have learners identify what renewable energy sources the federal government provides a subsidy for, such as solar and wind energy tax credits. Have learners gather evidence and create an argument for the subsidy of that renewable energy source.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host a debate in which learners are assigned roles (e.g., mayor, power company owner, solar power installer) and tasked with determining what investments their city or region should make. Provide learners with background text that has the information needed to make the argument on behalf of their role. For more advanced classrooms, allow learners enough time to research those perspectives on their own.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Note: This strategy supports &lt;strong&gt;CCR ELA Reading Anchor Strategy 6:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Assess how point of view or purpose shapes the content and style of a text&lt;/em&gt; (Pimentel, 2013, p.18) and &lt;strong&gt;CCR ELA Speaking and Listening Anchor Standard 3:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Evaluate a speaker’s point of view, reasoning, and use of evidence and rhetoric&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternatively, assign learners to debate about a historic or regionally-specific energy decision, such as the creation of a major power source like the Hoover Dam. Explore &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/hooverdam/educate/edpack0.html" target="_blank"&gt;instructional strategies&lt;/a&gt; around teaching about the Hoover Dam from the U.S. Department of the Interior, Bureau of Reclamation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Having learners participate in debates supports &lt;strong&gt;CCR Speaking and Listening Anchor Strategy 1:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Prepare for and participate effectively in a range of conversations and collaborations with diverse partners, building on others’ ideas and expressing their own clearly and persuasively&lt;/em&gt; (Pimentel, 2013, p. 30). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="graybox"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Learn More About It&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For foundational information on climate science and literacy, either for your own knowledge or to help frame instruction around climate and the environment, consider reading the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration resource, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://lincs.ed.gov/professional-development/resource-collections/profile-517" target="_blank"&gt;Climate Literacy: The Essential Principles of Climate Sciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This resource presents an overview of climate literacy and provides a springboard for investigation into many relevant subtopics within climate science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434467913</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="469">
        <pagenum>4</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Online Resources for Teaching Principle 5</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Online Resources for Teaching Principle 5&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spend some time exploring online resources related to this principle to support instruction. Here are a few examples to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Wub1_Dk_Ok" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Literacy Essential Principle #5&lt;/a&gt; video, from the U.S. Department of Energy and American Geoscience Institute, provides an overview of the principle, its concepts, and examples.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.energy101.com/calculators/" target="_blank"&gt;Energy101’s Energy Technology and Policy Energy Calculators&lt;/a&gt; are interactive computer-based tools that learners can use to see the effects of energy decisions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.energy101.com/free-educational-tools/videos/" target="_blank"&gt;Energy101’s videos&lt;/a&gt; cover energy, the economy, and the environment (see topic VII: Energy and Society).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2015/03/f20/EL5_SocStudiesGuides_AGI.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Literacy Social Studies Guides&lt;/a&gt; for Principle 5 guide learners through the research, gathering of evidence and supporting arguments about energy consumption and subsidies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This &lt;a href="http://fueleconomy.gov/feg/findacar.shtml"&gt;interactive tool&lt;/a&gt; on fuel economy allows learners to find and compare cars in terms of mileage, type of gas and type of car. This is a great introductory activity to jumpstart learners’ thinking about how their transportation choices impacts our global energy &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;consumption&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435856924</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="470">
        <pagenum>5</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Summary of Principle 5</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Summary of Principle 5&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 5 addresses how decisions are made regarding energy use. Individuals and societies make decisions about energy based on a wide range of factors, including political, economic, and environmental factors. This principle offers adult learners and ABE teachers opportunities to discuss the impact these decisions have on individuals and societies and to generate possible solutions to energy challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/LightBulbs.jpg" width="450" height="150" alt="Collection of compact fluorescent lamp (CFL), light-emitting diode (LED), and energy-saving incandescent light bulbs." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;All of these light bulbs meet the new energy standards that took effect from 2012-2014. (Photo by Dennis Schroeder / NREL. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;.) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #993300;"&gt;Continue on to Principle 6: The amount of energy used by human society depends on many factors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434029240</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
    </chapters>
  </book>
</activity>