<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<activity id="56" moduleid="4874" modulename="book" contextid="14181">
  <book id="56">
    <name>Principle 3: Biological processes depend on energy flow through the Earth system</name>
    <intro>&lt;p&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;</intro>
    <introformat>1</introformat>
    <numbering>0</numbering>
    <customtitles>1</customtitles>
    <timecreated>1433774493</timecreated>
    <timemodified>1433774493</timemodified>
    <chapters>
      <chapter id="453">
        <pagenum>1</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 3: Biological processes depend on energy flow through the Earth system</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Principle 3: Biological processes depend on energy flow through the Earth system.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/icon_p3.jpg" width="150" height="150" alt="Icon of a leaf to represent Principle 3 of the Energy Literacy Framework" style="float: right; margin-left: 20px; margin-right: 20px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle explores the flow of energy, beginning with the Sun, through various processes on Earth. This principle is an ideal way to explore systems and ecosystems. This principle includes many concrete processes that learners may already be familiar with, such as food chains. Teachers can incorporate many engaging visuals and animations to demonstrate these processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Principle 3’s Fundamental Concepts on the next page to build your understanding of the concepts and information included in each principle. You can use the Fundamental Concepts to inform your instruction related to this principle.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1433774647</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="454">
        <pagenum>2</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Principle 3’s Fundamental Concepts</title>
        <content>&lt;h1&gt;Principle 3’s Fundamental Concepts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fundamental Concepts of Principle 3 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.1  The Sun is the major source of energy for organisms and the ecosystems of which they are a part&lt;/strong&gt;. Producers such as plants, algae, and cyanobacteria use the energy from sunlight to make organic matter from carbon dioxide and water. This establishes the beginning of energy flow through almost all food webs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.2  Food is a biofuel used by organisms to acquire energy for internal living processes&lt;/strong&gt;. Food is composed of molecules that serve as fuel and building material for all organisms as energy stored in the molecules is released and used. The breakdown of food molecules enables cells to store energy in new molecules that are used to carry out the many functions of the cell and thus the organism.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3  Energy available to do useful work decreases as it is transferred from organism to organism&lt;/strong&gt;. The chemical elements that make up the molecules of living things are passed through food chains and are combined and recombined in different ways. At each level in a food chain, some energy is stored in newly made chemical structures, but most is dissipated into the environment. Continual input of energy, mostly from sunlight, keeps the process going.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.4  Energy flows through food webs in one direction, from producers to consumers and decomposer&lt;/strong&gt;s. An organism that eats lower on a food chain is more energy efficient than one eating higher on a food chain. Eating producers is the lowest, and thus most energy-&lt;span class="nolink"&gt;efficient&lt;/span&gt;, level at which an animal can eat.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.5  &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;Ecosystems&lt;/span&gt; are affected by changes in the availability of energy and matter&lt;/strong&gt;. The amount and kind of energy and matter available constrains the distribution and abundance of organisms in an ecosystem and the ability of the ecosystem to recycle materials.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.6  Humans are part of Earth’s &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;ecosystems&lt;/span&gt; and influence energy flow through these systems&lt;/strong&gt;. Humans are modifying the energy balance of Earth’s &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;ecosystems&lt;/span&gt; at an increasing rate. Shifts occur, for example, as a result of changes in agricultural and food processing technology, consumer habits, and human population size. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434544750</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="455">
        <pagenum>3</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Making Interdisciplinary Connections with Nutrition and Health Literacy Content</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Making Interdisciplinary Connections with Nutrition and Health Literacy Content&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presenting food as an energy source measured through calories is an easy way to make the energy flow process understandable and relevant. This is also an opportunity to make interdisciplinary connections with nutrition or health literacy content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore some online curriculum resources you can use to make those connections, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;a href="https://lincs.ed.gov/professional-development/resource-collections/profile-328" target="_blank"&gt;ESOL health literacy curriculum&lt;/a&gt; that includes lessons on healthy eating and the food pyramid (see number 16 in the publication's list of topics).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://lincs.ed.gov/professional-development/resource-collections/profile-330" target="_blank"&gt;ESOL lessons&lt;/a&gt; on Nutrition at the Intermediate and Advanced Beginning levels.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;a href="https://www.oercommons.org/courses/food-labels-tutorial" target="_blank"&gt;ABE lesson&lt;/a&gt; on food labels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;Have you successfully taught nutrition content in which you taught the concepts of carbohydrates, fats, and proteins as an energy unit (calories)? Share your tips and teaching strategies in the LINCS &lt;a href="https://community.lincs.ed.gov/discussion/online-course-using-health-concepts-teach-energy-literacy" target="_blank"&gt;Health Literacy group&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt; &lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/Banana_plant.jpg" width="350" height="547" alt="wer of a Grand Nain banana tree." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;The non-edible parts of the Grand Nain banana tree could be good biofuel. (Photo by Toshi Otsuki. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434465238</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="456">
        <pagenum>4</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Teaching about Water</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Bullet"&gt;Teaching about Water&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;Examining the water footprint of foods is a way to demonstrate the interconnectivity between food, water and energy. Learners can explore how much water is used to produce the foods they eat and how much energy is used to transport the food. Essential questions include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much water is used to make a hamburger versus growing an apple?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much energy is required to move that hamburger or apple across the country?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;To explore this interconnectivity, see the “&lt;a href="http://www.fao.org/nr/water/docs/WWD2012_howmuchwater_game.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;How Much Water” lesson&lt;/a&gt; from Food and Agriculture Organizations of the United Nations to use in your classroom. Print the images of the food and ask each learner to rank from least to greatest in terms of the amount of water used to produce that food. Learners can compare their ordering and ask each other questions on why they think the apple requires more water use than making orange juice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;Have learners try and create a low &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;w&lt;span class="nolink"&gt;ater footprint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;diet, by selecting foods that use less water to be produced. Learners can create a meal with food from the major food groups and make the connection between &lt;span class="nolink"&gt;water footprint&lt;/span&gt; and energy use in a meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Bullet"&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/PineappleFields.jpg" width="546" height="436" alt="Photo of pineapple fields on the north shore of Maui, Hawaii." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;Pineapple fields on the north shore of Maui, Hawaii that are drip irrigated with reclaimed sewage plant water. (Photo by Warren Gretz / NREL. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434482088</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="457">
        <pagenum>5</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Building Food Chains to Understand the Flow of Energy</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Building Food Chains to Understand the Flow of Energy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another teaching strategy involves using visuals and animations to teach the flow of energy through food chains and food webs. The &lt;a href="http://eschooltoday.com/ecosystems/what-is-a-foodchain.html"&gt;eSchoolToday&lt;/a&gt; website has a short interactive activity in which learners build a simple food chain, beginning with the energy of the sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learners can also manually create food chains and webs in a given ecosystem (e.g., ocean, lake, jungle). Or, to incorporate learners’ prior knowledge and connect food webs more closely to our lives, have learners create a food chain of your geographic region (e.g., desert, plains, city) or a food chain that ends with humans. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="396" height="261" alt="In the food web diagram, arrows show the direction of energy flow. It points to the animal doing the eating. Phytoplankton (or microalgae) is consumed by trout, dragonflies, and mayflies. Frogs and salamander consume dragonflies and mayflies. Snakes consume frogs and salamander. Bald eagles consume salamander; and humans consume trout. A basic food chain can be picked out from the web. For example, phytoplankton are consumed by trout and trout are consumed by humans. " src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/FoodWeb.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. (n.d.) Food web [Graphic]. Retrieved from &lt;a href="http://epa.gov/acidrain/education/site_students/foodweb.html"&gt;http://epa.gov/acidrain/education/site_students/foodweb.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435784743</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="458">
        <pagenum>6</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Other Teaching Strategies for Principle 3</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Other Teaching Strategies for Principle 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategies for incorporating Principle 3 into your instruction include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have learners listen to the radio story “&lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/thesalt/2012/06/27/155527365/visualizing-a-nation-of-meat-eaters"&gt;A Nation of Meat Eaters: See How It All Adds Up&lt;/a&gt;.” After listening, learners can review the supporting evidence on the website. To build on math skills and lessons, explore the graphs on the website, and have learners identify appropriate x and y axis labels. Learners can draw a conclusion about the connection of meat consumption and our energy use globally.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore agriculture practices through the&lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2015/03/f20/EL3_SocStudiesGuides_AGI.pdf" target="_blank"&gt; Energy Literacy Social Studies Guide&lt;/a&gt; for Principle 3 on where our food comes from and the energy used to transport food across the United States.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434466085</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="459">
        <pagenum>7</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Online Resources for Teaching Principle 3</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Online Resources for Teaching Principle 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online resources teachers can incorporate into their instruction for Principle 3 include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k6mX5uInCds" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Literacy Essential Principle #3&lt;/a&gt; video from the U.S. Department of Energy and American Geosciences Institute provides an overview of the principle, its concepts, and examples.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLEAN provides teaching suggestions and activities by level. Take a few moments to explore the materials on CLEAN's &lt;a href="http://cleanet.org/clean/literacy/energy3.html" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Principle 3&lt;/a&gt; web page and think about how you could use them with your learners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="266" height="400" style="line-height: 1.231;" alt="NREL researcher analyzing algae samples for oil content." src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/BeakerScientist.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;NREL researcher analyzing algae samples for oil content. (Photo by Pat Corkery / NREL. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435855148</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="460">
        <pagenum>8</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Summary of Principle 3</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Summary of Principle 3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 3 addresses the flow of energy through life on Earth, with the Sun as the primary source of energy for nearly all biological systems. This principle also illustrates the role of energy in food webs. The overall productivity of an ecosystem is controlled by the total energy available. The efficiency of the food chain decreases as you go upward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle is more concrete and easier to visualize than the first two principles, since everyone has direct experiences with different types of foods. Educators can use that experience to tie in an energy theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/CowGrazing.jpg" width="450" height="312" alt="Photo of a steer eating grass with a solar panel in the background." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="Graphic"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;Solar power is an economical way to pump water for livestock in remote ranch locations. (Photo by Shell Solar. Source: &lt;a href="http://images.nrel.gov/"&gt;http://images.nrel.gov/&lt;/a&gt;.) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="ALTtag"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="ALTtag"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="ALTtag"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #993300;"&gt;Continue on to Principle 4: Various sources of energy can be used to power human activities, and often this energy must be transferred from source to destination&lt;/span&gt;&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434466176</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
    </chapters>
  </book>
</activity>