<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<activity id="61" moduleid="4879" modulename="book" contextid="14186">
  <book id="61">
    <name>Course Conclusion</name>
    <intro>&lt;p class="Subhead"&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;</intro>
    <introformat>1</introformat>
    <numbering>0</numbering>
    <customtitles>1</customtitles>
    <timecreated>1433795596</timecreated>
    <timemodified>1433795596</timemodified>
    <chapters>
      <chapter id="482">
        <pagenum>1</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Wrap-Up Example – Integrating the Seven Essential Energy Principles in the ABE Classroom</title>
        <content>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;span&gt;Wrap-Up Example – Integrating the Seven Essential Energy Principles in the ABE Classroom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of how one instructor planned and delivered an energy literacy unit in an ABE classroom. As you go through the following example, think of how you might use a similar approach with your adult learners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin-left: 60px;"&gt;Gladys is an ABE teacher in an area where jobs in the clean energy sector are abundant. She decides to create a unit on energy to help the adult learners in her class become energy literate and begin thinking about clean energy jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin-left: 60px;"&gt;To help plan the unit, Gladys considers the jobs that are available in the area. These include solar panel installers and jobs in clean energy construction. She makes sure to include the vocabulary and relevant subjects needed for those jobs into her unit. She also explores the CLEAN website to review the teaching tips and instructional materials. This helps her narrow down the content she wants to cover in the allotted time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin-left: 60px;"&gt;To introduce the unit to her class, Gladys leads learners in a discussion on energy using the K-W-L strategy (handout is available in the &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2014/12/f19/EnergyLiteracy_StudentGuide_120214.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Student Guide&lt;/a&gt;). To get this discussion started, and provide fodder for content that learners may “want to know,” she shows the TED instructional video, &lt;a href="http://ed.ted.com/lessons/a-guide-to-the-energy-of-the-earth-joshua-m-sneideman" target="_blank"&gt;A Guide to the Energy of the Earth&lt;/a&gt;. This video has a lot of vocabulary and concepts that are new for her learners, but the interesting visuals keep them engaged. (For a higher level class, Gladys could substitute the U.S. Department of Energy’s &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zq3EFJ05fec" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Everywhere video&lt;/a&gt;, which provides an introduction to energy literacy.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin-left: 60px;"&gt;Gladys begins instruction of each principle by showing some of the videos available online (including the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLgU0cHea5t3omiamg-QK70Ff7vCsbP5QF" target="_blank"&gt;Energy Literacy Essential Principles&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLACD8E92715335CB2" target="_blank"&gt;Energy 101 videos&lt;/a&gt;). She tries to build on learners' background knowledge and looks for connections with learners’ lives and interests when she is selecting material and leading discussions. She also builds upon learners’ vocabulary knowledge by consistently using new and familiar vocabulary words in classroom materials and activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin-left: 60px;"&gt;As a capstone activity, she has learners write a five-paragraph essay defending an idea related to energy, drawing on and citing evidence learned throughout the unit.&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434472293</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="483">
        <pagenum>2</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Activity – Begin Planning an Energy Literacy Lesson or Unit</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Activity – Begin Planning an Energy Literacy Lesson or Unit&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have explored the seven principles in the Energy Literacy Framework, it’s time to apply what you have learned in this course and start creating your own energy literacy lesson or unit. Here are steps you can take to begin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Print out the Energy Literacy Framework or order copies by emailing &lt;a href="mailto:energyliteracy@ee.doe.gov"&gt;energyliteracy@ee.doe.gov&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Print the reference list at the end of this course and identify selected resources to explore further.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Look for ways to integrate other subjects, such as math, geography, social studies and writing, into the seven Energy Literacy Essential Principles. The strategies provided in this course are a good starting point.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;If you haven’t already done so, take the following LINCS courses, which focus on teaching science in the adult basic education/adult secondary education (ABE/ASE) classroom: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://lincs.ed.gov/learning-portal#science" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;i style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Engaging Adult Learners in Science&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; provides an overview of the relevance and importance of science in the ABE/ASE classroom and introduces the use of scientific practices.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://lincs.ed.gov/learning-portal#science" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;i style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Scientific Practices in Context: Curricular Planning and Lesson Development&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; provides guidance on where to find credible science resources, and an introduction to teaching science in context. It also reviews the teaching and learning cycle, focusing on curriculum design including lesson planning and development within the context of an adult education science unit.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://lincs.ed.gov/learning-portal#science" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;i style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Project-Based Science Instruction for Career Preparation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; makes connections between science content knowledge and how adults use science in their daily lives, especially in work and career-related contexts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review the Glossary at the end of this course to identify terms you might need to review or highlight in your unit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Start planning your energy literacy unit! You may want to consider creating a project-based lesson on energy with a focus on careers in the clean energy sector. For more information on energy career jobs, visit the following websites:    &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://energy.gov/eere/education/explore-clean-energy-careers" style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Explore Clean Energy Careers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; focuses on the names of jobs in renewable energy technology fields.  &lt;br /&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="file:///C:/Users/Grizz%20Twam%20-%20HP/Downloads/myenergygateway.com" style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;My Energy Gateway&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; allows learners to search for jobs and internships in different energy sectors. A description of the job and average salary range is also provided.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt;Career maps are online interactive tools that outline jobs in the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://energy.gov/eere/wind/wind-career-map" style="line-height: 1.231;" target="_blank"&gt;wind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://energy.gov/eere/sunshot/solar-career-map" style="line-height: 1.231;" target="_blank"&gt;solar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="line-height: 1.231;"&gt; industry. The maps provide information on the level (e.g., basic, advanced) salary, education requirements, competencies, and pathways for advancing in solar and wind sectors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As you work to create your lesson or unit plan, please share your ideas with others through the &lt;a href="https://community.lincs.ed.gov/group/science" target="_blank"&gt;LINCS Science Group&lt;/a&gt;. Include feedback from your learners and any lessons learned along the way.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider using the &lt;a href="https://lessonplanner.lincs.ed.gov/" target="_blank"&gt;LINCS Lesson Planner&lt;/a&gt; as a tool to help you create, save, and share your lessons.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope that you gained an understanding of energy literacy and the Essential Principles and Fundamental Concepts put forth in the Energy Literacy Framework. Hopefully, you are ready to employ strategies for teaching the seven principles to adult learners using a variety of online resources. If you feel you need more support from your colleagues who have also completed this course, consider reading and posting comments in the LINCS discussion threads embedded in this course. &lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434472452</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="484">
        <pagenum>3</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Participate in the Forum Discussions</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Participate in the Forum Discussions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on completing &lt;i&gt;Teaching Energy Literacy to Adult Learners&lt;/i&gt;&lt;em&gt;!&lt;/em&gt; We encourage you to stay involved in the LINCS Community and the &lt;a href="https://community.lincs.ed.gov/group/science" target="_blank"&gt;LINCS Science Group&lt;/a&gt; as you strive to integrate the seven essential principles in the Energy Literacy Framework into your classroom instruction. Take a few minutes to &lt;a href="https://community.lincs.ed.gov/discussion/online-course-teaching-energy-adult-learners" target="_blank"&gt;discuss&lt;/a&gt; and apply your newly acquired knowledge and learn about others' experiences in helping adult learners become energy literate.&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1433868665</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="485">
        <pagenum>4</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Course Conclusion</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Course Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This concludes the &lt;i&gt;Teaching Energy Literacy to Adult Learners&lt;/i&gt; course. We would like to thank the individuals and organizations who generously contributed to the design and development of this course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Michael Webber, Deputy Director of the Energy Institute at The University of Texas at Austin&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Erin Twamley, Adult Educator&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joshua Sneideman, Albert Einstein Distinguished Educator Fellow at the U.S. Department of Energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks are due to the Department of Energy Office of Energy Efficiency &amp;amp; Renewable Energy for developing and sharing the Energy Literacy Framework and associated materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that we can maintain the quality of our courses, we ask that you take a moment to complete the&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;a href="http://s-b4087e-i.sgizmo.com/s3/i-100012082-972844" target="_blank"&gt;course evaluation&lt;/a&gt;. Your feedback will ensure our courses meet your needs for professional development. Thank you.&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="graybox"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Access and Print Your Certificate Any Time&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on completing this LINCS Teaching Energy Literacy to Adult Learners course! To obtain your completion certificate, simply close this window and return to the course homepage. You will find a link for the completion certificate under the Course Conclusion and Resources section header.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: x-small;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Literacy Information and Communication System (LINCS) energy literacy course was developed by Kratos Learning for the U.S. Department of Education, Office of Career, Technical, and Adult Education under Contract No. ED-VAE-14-C-0123 . The opinions expressed herein do not necessarily represent the positions or policies of the U.S. Department of Education, and no official endorsement by the U.S. Department of Education should be inferred. This course is in the public domain and may be used without permission.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1438001211</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
    </chapters>
  </book>
</activity>