<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<activity id="53" moduleid="4871" modulename="book" contextid="14178">
  <book id="53">
    <name>Using the Energy Literacy Framework</name>
    <intro>&lt;p class="SessionPg1"&gt;&lt;a name="_Toc417393846"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Using the Energy Literacy Framework&lt;!--?xml:namespace prefix = "o" ns = "urn:schemas-microsoft-com:office:office" /--&gt;&lt;o:p&gt;&lt;/o:p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</intro>
    <introformat>1</introformat>
    <numbering>0</numbering>
    <customtitles>1</customtitles>
    <timecreated>1433369091</timecreated>
    <timemodified>1433369091</timemodified>
    <chapters>
      <chapter id="434">
        <pagenum>1</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>What Is Energy Literacy?</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;What Is Energy Literacy?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy literacy is an understanding of the nature and role of energy in the world and in our daily lives, accompanied by the ability to apply this understanding to answer questions and solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An energy-literate person:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can trace energy flows and think in terms of energy systems&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can identify positive and negative tradeoffs for different energy options, including different fuels and technologies&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;knows how much energy they use, for what purpose, and where the energy comes from&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can assess the credibility of information about energy&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can communicate about energy and energy use in meaningful ways&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is able to make informed energy use decisions based on an understanding of impacts and consequences&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/eere/education/energy-literacy-essential-principles-and-fundamental-concepts-energy-education"&gt;http://energy.gov/eere/education/energy-literacy-essential-principles-and-fundamental-concepts-energy-education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434460745</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="435">
        <pagenum>2</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>The Energy Literacy Framework</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;The Energy Literacy Framework&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of Energy spearheaded the development of &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2014/09/f18/Energy_Literacy_High_Res_3.0.pdf"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Energy Literacy: Essential Principles and Fundamental Concepts for Energy Education&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, referred to in this course as the Energy Literacy Framework. It is an interdisciplinary guide to teaching and learning about energy. The framework identifies seven Essential Principles and a set of Fundamental Concepts to support each principle. It does not seek to teach all areas of energy, but, rather, focuses on those that are essential for all citizens, regardless of age. The framework presents energy concepts that can help individuals and communities make informed energy decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434460909</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="436">
        <pagenum>3</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Interdisciplinary Energy Instruction</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Interdisciplinary Energy Instruction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adult educators should be aware that energy is a topic that can be taught through many different subject areas, including language arts, math, and social studies. The Energy Literacy Framework states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="margin-left: 30px;"&gt;Energy is an inherently interdisciplinary topic. Concepts fundamental to understanding energy arise in nearly all, if not all, academic disciplines. This guide is intended to be used across disciplines. Both an integrated and systems-based approach to understanding energy are strongly encouraged (p.2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of Energy has also created guides that showcase and describe social studies lessons and activities relevant to each Essential Principle. Links to the guides will be included later in this course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teaching these Essential Energy Literacy Principles can also support instruction that meets the &lt;a href="http://lincs.ed.gov/professional-development/resource-collections/profile-521"&gt;College and Career Readiness Standards (CCRS) for English Language Arts and Literacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: xx-small;"&gt;. &lt;span style="font-size: small;"&gt;The major shifts in the standards and how energy literacy content can meet those requirements are shown below.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; background-color: #ffffff;" border="1" rules="all" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5"&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr style="background-color: #0f24bc;"&gt;
&lt;td align="center" valign="middle" scope="col"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="color: #ffffff;"&gt; Standards Shift &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center" valign="middle" style="text-align: center;" scope="col"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="color: #ffffff;"&gt; Relevance &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: medium;"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="color: #ffffff;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center" valign="middle" style="text-align: center;" scope="col"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span medium="" strong=""&gt;&lt;span style="color: #ffffff;"&gt; Energy Literacy Connection  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align="left" valign="middle" style="text-align: left; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif; font-size: small;" scope="row" span=""&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: #ffffff;"&gt; &lt;b&gt;Shift 1 –  Complexity&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span style="background-color: #ffffff;"&gt; &lt;i&gt;Regular practice with complex text and its academic language&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 10pt;"&gt; Research indicates “that the complexity of text that students are able to read is the greatest predictor of success in college and careers” (Pimentel, 2013, p. 9). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 10pt;"&gt; Teaching about energy provides high-interest opportunities to incorporate increasingly complex and academic text into lessons. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align="left" valign="middle" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;" scope="row"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: #ffffff;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Shift 2 – Evidence: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: #ffffff;"&gt; &lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small;"&gt; Reading, writing , and speaking grounded in evidence from text, both literary and informational&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/i&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 10pt;"&gt; “National assessment data and input from college faculty indicates that command of evidence is a key college and career readiness skill” (Pimentel, 2013, p. 10). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 10pt;"&gt; Students learning about energy will be able to engage in discussions using evidence and scientific information they have read. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th align="left" valign="middle" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;" scope="row"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: #ffffff;"&gt; &lt;b&gt; Shift 3 – Knowledge: &lt;/b&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: #ffffff;"&gt;&lt;i&gt; Building knowledge through content-rich nonfiction &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 10pt;"&gt; A key focus of the CCRS standards is on “literacy across the disciplines of science, social science, and technical subjects” (Pimentel, 2013, p. 10). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align="center" style="border: 1px solid #000000; text-align: left;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: small; font-family: arial, helvetica, sans-serif;"&gt; &lt;span style="font-size: 10pt;"&gt; Energy is an interdisciplinary, technical topic that will help students build their content knowledge and potentially prepare for careers in this field.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1436477016</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="437">
        <pagenum>4</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Online Video Resources for Introducing the Energy Principles </title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Online Video Resources for Introducing the Energy Principles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To familiarize yourself with the seven Essential Principles, view the U.S. Department of Energy’s video, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zq3EFJ05fec"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Energy Everywhere – An Introduction to Energy Literacy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You might consider using this video to introduce an energy literacy unit to your learners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a simpler, engaging way to see the seven principles in action, watch the animated TED-Ed video, &lt;a href="http://ed.ted.com/lessons/a-guide-to-the-energy-of-the-earth-joshua-m-sneideman"&gt;A guide to the energy of the Earth&lt;/a&gt;. To learn more about how you can use this video in your classroom, create a login to access free TED-Ed materials, including supplemental questions to check learners’ understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434461189</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="438">
        <pagenum>5</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Video Series and Guides Introduce and Summarize the Essential Principles </title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Video Series and Guides Introduce and Summarize the Essential Principles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of Energy, in partnership with the Center for Geoscience and Society and the National Center for Science Education, has created a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLgU0cHea5t3omiamg-QK70Ff7vCsbP5QF"&gt;series of short videos &lt;/a&gt;that can be used to introduce and summarize the seven Essential Principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2014/12/f19/EnergyLiteracy_TeacherGuide_120914.pdf"&gt;Teacher Guide&lt;/a&gt; created for the series provides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tips for getting started when teaching an energy literacy unit&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideas for how to use the videos in instruction&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an illustrative example of how to teach a content area using each of the principles&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2014/12/f19/EnergyLiteracy_StudentGuide_120214.pdf"&gt;Student Analysis Guide &lt;/a&gt;can be used or adapted for use with adult learners. Strategies for using this guide include unpacking each of the questions and using them as a basis for classroom activities. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the “What do I &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline; font-size: small; color: #993300;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;k&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;now – What do I &lt;span style="text-decoration: underline; font-size: small; color: #993300;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;w&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ant to know – What did I&lt;span style="font-size: small;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline; font-size: small; color: #993300;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;l&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;earn” (KWL, chart) activity in the Student Guide as a way to kick off and wrap up each principle. Teachers can have learners complete the chart independently or as a group. This activity can serve as a formative assessment strategy for teachers to better understand where learners are and if they have learned the material.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Question #2 “Do you know where energy comes from?” and the suggested follow-up questions could be used to introduce the unit. The questions make the relevance of energy to our lives clear and can help build learners’ interest in the topic. Discuss the questions verbally or use them as writing prompts. Another idea is to present the questions as opportunities for investigation. Learners can work individually or in small groups to find the answers to the questions using the internet or other resources. Learners could report out their findings to the whole class.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow questions #4 through #10 to help learners become familiar with strategies for identifying unfamiliar or difficult terms and strategies for determining and comprehending their meanings. Depending on the reading level of the learners, teachers may have to provide varying levels of support and resources. For example, showing the relevant video prior to this activity may give lower-level readers more background knowledge and exposure to the vocabulary needed for the unit. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1434461253</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="439">
        <pagenum>6</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Applying the Seven Essential Principles</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Applying the Seven Essential Principles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are seven Essential Principles in the Energy Literacy Framework that explain basic and important ideas about energy and energy resources. Understanding and applying these principles allows people to make decisions with a more comprehensive awareness of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seven Essential Principles are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy is a physical quantity that follows precise natural laws.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical processes on Earth are the result of energy flow through the Earth system.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biological processes depend on energy flow through the Earth system.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various sources of energy can be used to power human activities, and often this energy must be transferred from source to destination.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy decisions are influenced by economic, political, environmental, and social factors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The amount of energy used by human society depends on many factors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The quality of life of individuals and societies is affected by energy choices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These principles provide a structure for delivering content in this topic. Principle 1 provides a natural starting point as it grounds learners in the concept of energy as a physical process. Principles 2 and 3 provide increasingly complex examples of how energy flow operates on Earth through the study of both familiar and new processes. Principles 4, 5, 6 and 7 include multiple opportunities for interdisciplinary instruction, as these principles emphasize the impact of energy and our choices related to energy on our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="680" height="534" alt="Chart listing the seven Energy Literacy Principles. 1) Energy is a physical quantity that follows precise natural laws. 2) Physical processes on Earth are the result of energy flow through the Earth system. 3) Biological processes depend on energy flow through the Earth system. 4) Various sources of energy can be used to power human activities, and often this energy must be transferred from source to destination. 5) Energy decisions are influenced by economic, political, environmental, and social factors. 6) The amount of energy used by human society depends on many factors. 7) The quality of life of individuals and societies is affected by energy choices." src="@@PLUGINFILE@@/Energy7principles.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1435781964</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="440">
        <pagenum>7</pagenum>
        <subchapter>0</subchapter>
        <title>Fundamental Concepts Clarify Energy Principles</title>
        <content>&lt;h1 class="Subhead"&gt;Fundamental Concepts Clarify Energy Principles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concepts are important components that comprise each principle. The Fundamental Concepts given in the Framework provide more specific information about the suggested content for instruction within each principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remainder of this course highlights the Fundamental Concepts, and includes suggested classroom materials and teaching strategies for incorporating each of the Essential Principles into your instruction. As you learn about the principles and their associated concepts, think about how you can use them to teach science content to the adult learners in your classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="color: #993300;"&gt;Continue on to Principle 1: Energy is a physical quantity that follows precise natural laws.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <contentformat>1</contentformat>
        <hidden>0</hidden>
        <timemodified>1433712061</timemodified>
        <importsrc></importsrc>
      </chapter>
    </chapters>
  </book>
</activity>